- A plane plummets out of the sky,
一架飞机从天而降
a speed runner inexplicably jumps to a higher platform.
一位速通玩家不知怎地就跳到了更高的平台上
- What the?
什么？
What the?
这也可以？
- And an election recount is triggered.
一次选举启动重新计票
All because of the same invisible phenomenon
所有这一切都源于宇宙中弥漫的同一种无形现象
that permeates the universe.
On May 18th, 2003, voters in Belgium went to the polls.
在2003年5月18日，比利时选民前往投票站
In many regions, voting was done on a computer,
在许多地区，比利时人十几年来一直在试验使用电脑投票
something the Belgians had been experimenting with
for over a decade.
But the system had a backup.
而且系统是有备份的
Each voter would insert a magnetic card into the machine
每位选民把磁卡插入机器
and make their selection on screen.
然后在屏幕上进行他们的选择
Their vote was saved both to the computer
他们的选票同时保存在计算机
and the magnetic card,
和磁卡中
which they dropped into a box for redundancy.
并把他们放入箱子中，以备不时之需
Late that night, as the votes were being tabulated,
当日深夜，在制作选票的表格时
one of the election officials detected a problem
一名选举官员发现
with the results from Schaerbeek,
布鲁塞尔市中心斯哈尔贝克的
a municipality in central Brussels.
选票结果存在问题
Maria Vindevogel, a little known candidate
Maria Vindevogel是一位没什么名气的候选人
with her own party received more votes
相比于数学上的可能结果
than was mathematically possible.
她所在的政党获得了更多的选票
They knew this because of the way
他们知道这一点的原因是
the preferential voting system works.
由于优先投票制的运作方式
So they took out the magnetic cards and started a recount.
于是他们拿出磁卡，开始重新计票
One by one, they fed each of them
他们一个接一个把磁卡再次投入机器
through the machines again,
and after several hours, the recount was complete.
几小时后，重新计票完成
The vote totals for every candidate
每个候选人的总选票数与之前完全相同
were exactly the same as before,
except for Maria Vindevogel.
除了Maria Vindevogel
In her case, the recounted number of votes
在她选票有变的情况下，重新计票的票数
was less than the original by 4,096.
比原来少了4096票
So what went wrong?
那什么出问题了呢
How had her original tally
她的原始票数是如何被4000多票抬高的？
been inflated by over 4,000 votes?
Computer experts were brought in to run extensive tests
他们请来计算机专家对该软件进行大量测试
on the software.
They combed through the code, but could find no bugs.
他们梳理了代码，但是什么错误都没找到
They got the computer
他们拿到了产生初始计算错误的计算机
that had made the initial erroneous tally
and tested the hardware again and again,
然后一次又一次测试硬件
but they could not replicate the error.
但他们无法复现错误
Everything about the hardware
硬件一切的一切似乎都在完美工作状态
seemed to be in perfect working order.
And this left only one possible explanation
这就只剩下一种解释
and it is seriously weird.
而且这个解释非常非常奇怪
The clue comes from the excess number of votes
线索来自Vindevogel获得的过多选票
Vindevogel received.
4,096.
Computers work using binary, strings of zeros and ones,
计算机使用二进制，0和1的字符串工作
each corresponding to a power of two.
每一个字符串对应2的幂
So somewhere inside the computer tabulating all the votes
因此，在计算机内的某处，
was a string of bits
计算所有选票的是一个字符串位，
representing the number of votes Maria received.
代表Maria获得的所有选票
It started the day all zeros,
开始都是0
and then as each vote for her came in,
然后随着每次有选票投她
it would increment by one.
都会增加1
Physically, this is done by turning on a transistor for one
物理上讲，这是通过开启晶体管为1
and turning it off for zero.
关闭晶体管为0实现的
What's remarkable about the number 4,096
数字4096的特别之处在于它恰好是2的幂
is that it is exactly a power of two.
Two to the power of 12.
2的12次方
That is the 13th bit.
这是第13位
So for Maria Vindevogel to receive an extra 4,096 votes,
因此，想让Maria Vindevogel获得额外的4096张票
only one thing needed to happen.
只需要让一件事发声
The 13th bit had to flip from a zero to a one.
第13位必须从0反转到1
But why would that happen?
但为什么会这样呢
Computers work precisely because bits don't flip
计算机可以正常工作正是因为位并不会反转
unless we want them to, or do they?
除非我们希望它们反转，或者它们自己想？
Looking into the problem,
在调查这个问题时，
Belgian investigators found reports of similar issues
比利时调查人员发现从1970年代开始大型计算机公司有类似问题报告
from big computer companies starting in the 1970s.
In 1978, Intel reported some strange errors popping up
1978年，英特尔报告称
in their 16 kilobit dynamic random access memory or DRAM.
其16 KB动态内存（DRAM）中出现了一些奇怪的错误
动态随机存取存储器，或动态内存（DRAM）
需要周期性地充电来保持数据
因而得名“动态”
而如今常用的内存为“静态”内存
Ones would spontaneously flip to zeros with no apparent cause.
有些“1”会毫无征兆地自动归“0”
The problem turned out to be
问题原来出在
the ceramic packaging the chip was encased in.
用于封装芯片的陶瓷上
With the demand for semiconductor packaging skyrocketing
随着1970年代对半导体封装需求的激增
in the 1970s, a new manufacturing plant was constructed
一家新的制造厂被建立在了
on the Green River in Colorado.
科罗拉多州的格林河附近
Unfortunately, this site happened to be
不幸的是  这家制造厂正好位于
just downstream of an old uranium mill.
一个旧铀厂的下游
Radioactive atoms made their way into the river
放射性原子进入河流
and then into the ceramic packaging for Intel's microchips.
然后进入英特尔芯片的陶瓷封装
Intel scientists investigating the problem found that
调查这个问题的英特尔科学家发现
even trace amounts of uranium and thorium in the ceramic
即便是陶瓷中痕量的铀和钍
were sufficient to cause problems.
也足以引起问题
In their DRAM, memory was stored as the presence
在英特尔的DRAM中
or absence of electrons in a semiconductor well.
他们以半导体阱中的电子存在与否来存储0和1
The alpha particles emitted by uranium and thorium
铀和钍发射的α粒子
were energetic and ionizing enough
能量充足并且电离能力极强
to create electron hole pairs in the silicone.
足以在硅中产生电子空穴对
If an alpha particle is struck in just the right place,
如果α粒子撞击的位置正确
it could create a large number of free charge carriers
它可能会产生大量的自由电荷载流子
causing electrons to accumulate in the well
导致电子在阱中堆积
flipping a one to a zero.
将1翻转为0
This is known as a single event upset, a type of soft error.
这被称为单粒子翻转，是一种软性错误
The error is soft because the device hasn't been damaged.
之所以说是“软”错误，是因为设备并没有损坏
The bit has changed,
某一位发生了变化
but you could erase it and rewrite it with no problems.
但你可以毫无问题地将其擦除并重写
Investigators exposed the chips to alpha emitters
研究人员将芯片暴露在
with different levels of activity.
不同强度的α射线中
And just as you'd expect,
不出所料
they found the number of bit flips directly correlated
他们发现位翻转发生的频率
with the number of alpha particles
与芯片所在环境中α粒子的数量
the chip had been exposed to.
有着直接的关系
The reason this problem was identified in the 1970s
之所以在上世纪70年代会发现这个问题
was because chip components had been miniaturized
是因为那时的芯片组件已经小到
to the point where a single alpha particle
只要有单个α粒子
could produce enough charge to flip a bit.
就能产生足够的电荷  使某一位发生翻转
Immediately, these findings attracted a lot of attention.
这些发现随即引起了大量关注
Before the paper was published,
在论文被发表前
it was widely circulated in the industry.
它们已经在业内广为流传
And as a result, chip manufacturers were a lot more careful
这让芯片制造商变得更加谨慎
to avoid radioactive materials
以免在生产和封装芯片时
when producing their microchips and packaging.
使用了带有放射性的原料
Therefore, the bit flip that gave Maria Vindevogel
因此，让玛丽亚·温德沃格尔获得
4,096 extra votes
额外4096票的位翻转
wasn't caused by natural radioactivity in the computer.
并不是由计算机中的自然放射性引起的
So where did it come from?
那么它是从哪里来的呢
After Henri Becquerel discovered radioactivity
1896年  亨利·贝克勒尔发现铀具有放射性后
with uranium in 1896,
scientists sought a way to measure it.
科学家们开始寻找测量它的方法
How radioactive were different materials?
不同材料的放射性如何
And one way to do this is with a gold leaf electrometer.
一种测量方法是使用金箔静电计
When it's charged, the leaf is repelled
当它被充能时，金箔会产生张角
and you can measure the amount of charge
你就可以通过金箔抬起的角度
by the angle of the leaf.
来测量电荷量
Now, if ionizing radiation enters the chamber,
现在，如果电离辐射进入静电计
it rips electrons off air molecules,
它会从空气中剥离出电子
creating positive and negative charges.
产生正电荷和负电荷
Opposite charges are attracted to the leaf,
相反的电荷被吸引到金箔上
discharging it over time.
导致其随着时间的推移而放电
The higher the level of ionizing radiation,
电离辐射的强度越高
the faster the device discharges.
静电计放电就越快
In 1910, Theodore Wolf took his electrometer
1910年，西奥多·沃尔夫带着他的静电计
to the top of the Eiffel Tower.
来到了艾菲尔铁塔的顶端
Since radioactivity was found in the soil and rocks of earth,
由于人们已在地球的土壤和岩石中  发现了放射性
he expected that 300 meters up,
他认为在距离地表300米高的地方
the radiation would be just a few percent
那里的放射性
of the ground radiation.
应该只有地表的百分之几
Instead he found only a slight decrease.
然而  他却仅观测到了轻微的下降
In 1911, Austrian physicist Victor Hess
1911年  奥地利物理学家维克托·赫斯
decided to take this experiment further.
决定走得更远
Literally.
字面意思的“更远”
He loaded electric scopes into the basket of a hydrogen balloon.
他把电镜装进氢气球的篮子里
In his first two flights,
在他的前两次飞行中
he observed the same thing as Wolf.
他观测到的结果与沃尔夫相同
Up to an altitude of 1100 meters,
在高达1100米的地方
both trips revealed no fundamental change in radiation
两趟观测都显示 与地表相比
compared to the values observed on the ground.
辐射没有本质变化
But the next year, he conducted seven balloon flights
但是第二年，他进行了七次气球飞行
up to an altitude of 5,200 meters.
升至5200米的高度
And here he discovered something remarkable.
他在这里发现了一些了不得的东西
While there was an initial drop in radiation
虽然在最初的几百米内
for the first several hundred meters,
辐射开始下降
above one kilometer or so
但超过一千米左右
the level increased with increasing altitude.
辐射水平随着高度的增加而增加
At his maximum height,
在他所能达到的最大高度
the level of radiation was several times greater
那里的辐射水平
than it was on the ground.
是地表的几倍
The radiation appeared to be coming, not from the earth,
辐射似乎不是来自地球
but from the sky.
而是来自天空
Hess scheduled one of his balloon flights
赫斯在日食期间
during a solar eclipse.
安排了一次气球飞行
And as the moon passed in front of the sun,
当月球从太阳前经过时
he carefully watched his instruments.
他认真地盯着他的仪器
But the readings were unaffected.
但读数并没有受影响
Even with the sun half covered,
即使太阳被遮住了一半
the level of radiation was the same.
辐射水平也是一样的
Since no influence of the eclipse
由于没有观测到
on the penetrating radiation was noted,
日食对辐射的影响
we conclude that
我们得出结论
even if a part of the radiation should be of cosmic origin,
即使那部分辐射的来源是宇宙
it hardly emanates from the sun.
它也几乎不来自于太阳
Victor Hess had discovered cosmic rays.
维克托·赫斯发现了宇宙射线
High energy radiation from space.
来自太空的高能辐射
But what were these rays exactly
但是这些射线究竟是什么呢
and where were they coming from?
它们又从哪来呢
Well, today we know they aren't electromagnetic rays
不像之前人们认为它们是电磁波
as many suspected, but particles.
今天我们知道它们是粒子
Around 90% are protons,
其中大约90%是质子
9% are helium nuclei, and 1% are heavier nuclei.
9%是氦核 1%是更重的核素
比氢氦重的都是金属
Some of them are from the sun,
它们当中有些来自太阳
but they have comparatively low energy.
具有的能量相对较低
High energy cosmic rays moving very close
高能宇宙射线被银河系和其他星系的
to the speed of light come from exploding stars, supernova
恒星爆炸 超新星事件
in our own galaxy and in others.
加速到接近光速
And the highest energy particles
而能量最高的粒子
are thought to come from black holes,
则被认为来自黑洞
including the super massive black holes at the centers of galaxies.
包括星系中心的超大质量黑洞
But it's hard to pin down
但是很难搞清楚
exactly where cosmic rays come from
宇宙射线到底是从哪里来的
because as charged particles,
因为它们是带电粒子
they're deflected by magnetic fields in space.
会被空间中的磁场改变方向
So they can wind their way through the universe
for billions of years.
所以它们会在宇宙中曲折穿行数十亿年
A cosmic ray detected on October 15th, 1991
1991年10月15日探测到的一条宇宙线
had an energy of 51 joules.
其能量达到了51焦耳
That is a single subatomic particle
这是一个亚原子粒子
with the energy of a baseball going 100 kph.
动能相当于一个有百公里时速的棒球
For obvious reasons, it was dubbed the OMG particle.
出于很明显的原因（粒子动能极大），它被称作OMG粒子
一些参考 http://www.fourmilab.ch/documents/OhMyGodParticle/
似乎没有正式译名
But primary cosmic rays like these
但是像那样的初级宇宙线
don't make it down to earth's surface.
不会到达地表
Instead, they collide with air molecules
它们会和距地面约25km的大气中的分子碰撞
around 25 kilometers above the ground
and create new particles like pions.
产生新的粒子 如π介子
These collide and decay into other particles like neutrons,
这些粒子再次碰撞和衰变产生其他粒子 如中子
protons, muons, electrons, positrons and photons,
质子 μ子 电子 正电子 和光子
which in turn collide with other air molecules
这些粒子又与其他空气分子碰撞
in one long cascade.
产生级联效应
So from a single primary cosmic ray,
所以从一个初级宇宙粒子
comes a shower of particles streaming towards the earth.
会产生一阵向地表倾泻的粒子流
It is one of these particles that investigators
人们怀疑正是这些粒子中的一个
suspect struck a transistor in a computer in Belgium,
击中了比利时一台电脑上的晶体管
flipping the 13th bit from a zero to a one
将第13比特从0翻转到1
and giving Maria Vindevogel 4,096 extra votes.
给Maria Vindevogel增加了4096张额外选票
But how often do things like this happen?
但是这些事情多久发生一次
In 1911, Charles Wilson
1911年  查尔斯威尔逊（的研究）
made it possible to see the cosmic rays all around us
让我们得以观察周围环境中的宇宙射线
when he perfected his cloud chamber,
他完善了自己的云室
an enclosure with super saturated water or alcohol vapor.
这是个封闭容器  里面充满了过饱和的水蒸汽或酒精蒸气
When a cosmic ray passes through the chamber,
当一个宇宙线粒子穿过云室
it ionizes the gas causing vapor to condense
电离气体导致蒸汽凝结
into tiny droplets on the ions,
产生附着在离子上的小液滴
revealing the path of the particle.
揭示粒子的运动路径
Alpha particles, helium nuclei, leave short thick tracks
α粒子（即氦核）会留下短而粗的轨迹
while beta particles, electrons leave long skinny trails.
而β粒子（即电子）会则留下细长的尾迹
In 1932, Carl Anderson identified a trail
1932年 卡尔·安德森发现了一条特殊的轨迹
that looked like it was made by an electron,
看似由电子产生
but in the applied magnetic field, it curved in the wrong direction.
但它在外加磁场中向相反方向偏转
Implying it had a positive charge.
这说明它带有正电荷
Anderson had found the anti electron or positron.
由此安德森发现了“反电子” 或曰“正电子”
It was the first confirmed sighting of anti-matter.
这是人类首次发现反物质的存在
Four years later, also using a cloud chamber,
四年之后 也是在云室中
he discovered the muon, again in cosmic rays.
他发现了宇宙线中的μ子
For his discovery of the positron,
由于正电子的发现
Anderson was awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1936.
安德森获得了1936年的诺贝尔物理学奖
He shared the prize with Victor Hess,
他与维克托·赫斯分享了奖项
the man who discovered cosmic rays in the first place,
后者首次发现了宇宙射线
invisible particles that affect our lives in ways
在不经意中影响我们生活的
most of us are oblivious to.
不可见粒子
This is possibly the rarest thing
这可能是电子游戏史上
to ever happen in a video game.
发生过最离谱的事情
In 2013, user DOTA_Teabag was speed running
2013 年，玩家 DOTA_Teabag 正在主机上速通超马 64
Super Mario 64 on the console.
In the level Tik Tok Clock,
在打“摇摆古钟”这一关时
he suddenly up warps onto a higher platform.
他突然跳到了天花板上面
- What the?
- 这啥？
- Did you get invisible wall?
你卡到空气墙里了？
What? - Please say you got the---
啥？ - 你卡到...
- No, that was the craziest thing
- 不，这是我见过
I've ever seen though.
最离谱的事情
- The move shaves off a few seconds
画面卡了几秒
and it seems like a newly discovered glitch in the game
然后看上去像找到了游戏新 bug 一样
that could give speed runners an edge.
给速通玩家一个捷径
User PenandCook12 put out a $1,000 bounty
PenandCook12 发出 1000 美金赏金
for anyone who could replicate the up warp.
给能够复现这个操作的玩家
But so far, after six years,
但是在六年后
no one has been able to.
还是没人能够做到
The best explanation anyone can come up with
目前最合理的解释是
is that a cosmic ray caused the glitch.
宇宙射线造成了这个 bug
It's been shown that a single bit flipped
有人证实 把马里奥高度坐标
in the first bit of Mario's height co-ordinate
的其中一位翻转
could have caused the effect.
就可以实现这个效果
On the main level, the byte was 1 1 0 0 0 1 0 1.
正常情况下，这个坐标表示为 11000101
But if you flip the last one to a zero,
但是如果你把最后一位翻转成 0
it changes his vertical position.
它的高度坐标将会被改变
And just by chance,
而正巧
this new height coincides with the higher floor.
这正是天花板的坐标
PenandCook12 wrote a script
PenandCook12 写了一个脚本
to manually flip the bit at the right moment
来在合适的时候翻转这一位
and was able to achieve the same up warp.
它能成功复现同样的效果
This is a particularly visible bit flip,
这是一个挺明显的位翻转
but the truth is cosmic rays are triggering bit flips all the time.
但是事实是 宇宙射线造成的位翻转时刻在发生
- An upset there, transient there
- 比较麻烦的是 宇宙射线的影响
can alter the function of these devices
能够改变这些设备的功能
and we call that a single event functional interrupt.
我们把它称作单事件功能性中断
So an entire process can hang.
整个进程都会卡住
So a blue screen of death that you get
所以你电脑的蓝屏
might actually have been a neutron or whatnot.
可能就是一个中子啥的引起的
- When people see the blue screen of death,
- 当人们电脑蓝屏的时候
could that be caused by a cosmic ray?
可能会是宇宙射线引起的吗
- Absolutely.
- 当然
- These days, there are a number of ways
- 现如今，计算机芯片有许多方法
computer chips are made resilient in the face of bit flips
来减少宇宙射线的干扰
like error correction code or ECC memory.
例如纠错码和 ECC 内存
But you can't totally prevent bit flips from happening.
但是你没法完全阻止位翻转发生
In 1996, IBM estimated that for each 256 megabytes of RAM,
1996 年，IBM 提出预计  每 256M 内存
one bit flip occurs per month.
每个月会发生一次位翻转
And the main culprit seems to be
而罪魁祸首应该是
neutrons created in the shower of particles from cosmic rays.
宇宙射线粒子流里的中子
Starting in 2009,
2009 年开始
Toyota recalled millions of vehicles
丰田召回了数以百万的汽车
due to the problem of unintended acceleration.
这些车会突然加速
- We were in the fast lane driving at about 70,
- 我们在高速车道上以 70 码的速度开着
and he said that the car was continuing to accelerate
他说这车怎么一直加速
and he couldn't bring it to a stop.
根本停不下来
- Many speculated that cosmic ray induced bit flips
- 许多人怀疑问题原因是宇宙射线造成
in the electronic control system were the cause.
电子系统里的位翻转
So much so that NASA was called in to help with the investigation.
因此 NASA 被叫来参与调查
But it turns out, cosmic rays were probably not the culprit.
但是结果是 宇宙射线可能并不是原因
NASA identified as the main causes,
NASA 认为主要原因是
sticky accelerator pedals,
油门太黏了
poorly fitted floor mats
地毯松动
and most commonly, drivers pushing on the accelerator
而最常见的情况是  驾驶员把油门当成了刹车
thinking it was the brake.
But cosmic rays have caused crashes of supercomputers,
但是宇宙射线造成了超级计算机的崩溃
especially at higher elevations.
特别是建在高处的计算机
Los Alamos National Labs located 2200 meters above sea level
洛斯阿拉莫斯国家实验室  建在海拔 2200 米的地方
is constantly dealing with neutron induced supercomputer crashes.
那里无时无刻不在处理“中子导致超算崩溃”的问题
So the software auto saves frequently
所以这里的软件高频保存
and neutron detectors have been installed throughout the facility.
还到处安装了中子检测器
If you go even higher,
如果高度再高一些
like climbing up to cruising altitude in a plane,
例如当飞机爬升至巡航高度的情况下
you can see the radiation from cosmic rays increasing on a Geiger counter.
你可以在盖革计数器上  观测到逐渐增强的宇宙射线辐射
To .5 microsieverts per hour at 18,000 feet.
在 5500 米的高度下  辐射量是每小时 0.5 微西弗
Up to one microsieverts per hour at 23,000 feet.
在 7000 米高度下是每小时 1 微西弗
Over two microsieverts per hour at 33,000 feet.
在 1 万米高度下  则超过了每小时 2 微西弗
And over three microsieverts per hour
如果再高一些 或距离极点更近一些
at even higher altitudes and towards the poles.
甚至可以达到每小时 3 微西弗
At cruising altitude,
在巡航高度下
this increases the chance of a single event upset by 10 to 30 times.
这能让单粒子翻转发生的概率提高 10 到 30 倍
This isn't critical if it happens in your laptop,
它发生在笔记本电脑上并不严重
but what if it occurs in the flight computer?
那对于飞控电脑来说呢
On October 7th, 2008,
2008 年 10 月 7 日
an Airbus A330 took off from Singapore to Perth.
一架飞往澳大利亚珀斯的空客 A330 从新加坡起飞
Just over three hours into the flight,
仅仅过了三个小时
the plane suddenly pitched down
飞机突然就开始压下机头
diving 200 meters in 20 seconds.
在 20 秒内下坠了近 200 米
Inside the plane, everyone experienced negative 0.8 Gs
在飞机里 所有人都承受着负 0.8 倍的
of acceleration.
重力加速度
It would have felt like the plane had flipped over.
这种感觉就像是飞机以翻转的姿态飞行
- The G-Force was enough,
- 这个 G 力非常强大
even with our three point harness
甚至连三点式安全带都绑不住
to lift us both out of the seat
我们飞出了座位
and push us forward as well.
被推向了仪表
- Minutes later, the plane dropped another 120 meters.
过了一分钟 飞机又下坠了 120 米
119 people on board were injured,
119 人受伤
many from bumping their heads into the ceiling.
很多人头部顶穿了天花板
So the pilots decided to make an emergency landing in Learmonth.
所以机长决定 在里尔蒙斯机场紧急降落
In the investigation that followed, the fault seem to occur
随后的调查显示 故障似乎是出现在
with the first air data inertial reference unit,
第一个大气数据惯性基准单元上
or ADIRU for short.
它简称 ADIRU
This computer supplies critical data
这个器件提供重要的飞行数据
like airspeed, angle of attack and altitude.
比如空速 迎角以及飞行高度
The way it supplies each of these pieces of information
它提供这些数据的方式
is in a 32 bit binary word.
是把它存在一个 32 比特的字里面
The first eight bits identify the type of information
前 8 位表示数据类型
and bits 11 to 29 encode the actual data.
11 到 29 位表示实际数据
What seems to have happened
当时的情况似乎是
is that a bit flip in the first eight bits
前 8 位中的某一位被翻转了
meant altitude information was mislabeled
也就是说 这个数据被错标成了迎角参数
as angle of attack information.
而不是高度参数
Inside the cockpit, alarms went on
在驾驶舱里 超速和失速的警报
for over speed and stall simultaneously,
一直在同时响
something that should be impossible.
这种情况按道理不可能出现
But the plane nose down sharply to correct what it thought was a stall,
但飞控电脑认为它在失速 于是降下机头
throwing passengers and crew into the ceiling.
机组人员和乘客因此被抛上了天花板
Investigators looked into software bugs,
调查员分析了软件错误
software corruption, a hardware fail,
软件损坏 硬件故障
physical environment factors
物理环境因素
and electromagnetic interference.
甚至电磁干扰
But each of these possibilities was found to be unlikely
但这些可能性都被已经掌握的
based on multiple sources of evidence.
多方证据排除了
The other potential triggering event
那么造成这起事件的原因可能就是
was a single event effect
单粒子效应所导致的
resulting from a high energy atmospheric particle
一个高能带电的大气粒子
striking one of the integrated circuits
击中了 CPU 模块里的
within the CPU module.
一个集成电路
One of the challenges with single event upsets
单粒子翻转所带来的一个挑战是
is that they are soft errors.
它们造成的都是软错误
They don't leave a trace,
它搞事情不留痕迹
but interestingly, the Airbus A330 was built in 1992
但有趣的是 这架空客 A330 是在 1992 年建造的
when there were no specific regulatory
当时没有具体的法律规章或航空器制造商会要求
or aircraft manufacturer requirements
for airborne systems to be resilient to single event effects.
航空器在设计时 必须能够耐受单粒子翻转的影响
With the space shuttle,
但对于航天飞机来说
redundancy was built in from the start.
这类规定一开始就已经制定
For navigation and control, there were four computers
有四台电脑同时运行着同样的系统
simultaneously running identical software.
来负责导航和飞行控制
If one computer had a soft error,
如果其中一台电脑出现软故障
the other three would overrule it.
另外三台就会接管它
And using this setup,
利用这套配置
they could also track the frequency of bit flips.
还可以统计出发生软故障的频率
On one five day mission, STS 48,
在一次长达 5 日的航天任务 STS-48 中
there were 161 separate bit flips.
分别出现了 161 次比特位翻转的情况
Above the atmosphere, cosmic rays are so energetic
在大气层以外  宇宙射线的能量要更充沛
sometimes you can even see them.
以至于你有时可以用肉眼看见它们
- Once in a while you have your eyes closed
有时候  你已经上床闭眼
and you're not asleep yet.
但还没睡熟
And if you wait a little while,
等上一会儿
you occasionally will see a flash of light.
你偶尔能“看到”闪光
And we think it is heavy particles
这应该是重粒子
or individual bursts of energy coming from radiation
即辐射中携带能量的个体
that are either going through the eyeball itself
穿过了眼球或感光神经
or going through the optic nerve.
And they,
然后
the way that your body registers radiation going through it
你的身体就以给你看一道闪光的神奇方式
is amazingly enough by showing you a little flash in one of your eyes,
记录下辐射穿过的瞬间
just to remind you that
这也是在提醒你
you are subject to the radiation of not only our sun,
除了太阳以外
but every star of the universe, that is radiating at you.
来自宇宙中每一颗星星的辐射  都有可能到达你这里
I picture back to the first astronauts
我能想像第一批宇航员
who must have closed their eyes and seen that radiation and gone,
闭上眼睛然后看到辐射之后的场景：
"I'm not going to tell anybody about this
“啊这 我跟谁都不会讲的”
"because no one's told me about it.
“没人说过会有这种现象啊”
"I'm not talking."
“打死也不说”
I can just imagine the first two guys that said,
我也能想象第一次谈论这个话题的两个家伙
"Hey, I am,
“嘿 我说，
"sometimes I see flashes of light.
有的时候...这眼前会出现闪光诶
"Do you see flashes of light?"
“诶你也看得到吗？”
And then it's, "Oh, we all see flashes of light."
“哦，原来大家都看到了啊”
"Oh, okay, well, that's all right then."
“那没事了，看起来是正常现象”
- For missions to other planets,
前往其他星球的航天任务
protecting electronics is critical.
更需要保护好电子设备
- If a single bit of information
如果控制飞船关键部分信息的一个比特
controls a critical function on your spacecraft,
let's say your thrusters,
比如说控制助推器的一个比特
and that goes from a one to is zero, from a on to off,
从1变成了0，从通变成了断，或者反过来
or vice versa, you could lose the mission.
可能整个任务就毁了
- That's why the computer
这就是为什么最近在火星着陆的毅力号火星车
on the Perseverance Rover that just landed on Mars
is 20 years old.
搭载的是20年前
It's a power PC launched in 2001
2001年推出的PowerPC处理器
with only 256 megabytes of Ram
只有256MB的内存
and two gigabytes of flash storage.
和2GB的闪存
But it is radiation hardened,
但它挡辐射是一把好手
meaning the design, materials, circuits and software
专门的设计、材料、线路和软件
are built to withstand 40 times the radiation
使它能抵抗的辐射量是正常电脑所能承受的40倍
of an ordinary computer.
It's been used on over a dozen space missions going back to 2005.
自2005年来  这台电脑已在十余次太空任务中发挥功用
- In fact, when we first started doing the power PC testing
我们多年前开始测试PowerPC的时候
years ago, the way we did it,
we just simply stuck an operating system processor
就是把一个处理器卡在粒子流上
in a beam line where we generate these particles
这样就能在地球上模拟粒子撞击
on the planet and look for blue screens of death.
然后看看电脑会不会蓝屏
You can kind of figure out what's going wrong
之后就是找出问题
and try to undo that.
解决问题
So you don't get to the blue screen of death
直到电脑不再蓝屏
because a spacecraft that gets into that mode
因为要是太空中电脑蓝屏了
is basically unrecoverable.
那基本上就凉凉了
- As the Voyager 1 spacecraft departed the solar system,
旅行者1号驶离太阳系的标志之一
one of the ways we could tell was by an increase
就是它遭受的宇宙射线的流量增大了
in the flux of cosmic rays it experienced.
Although on earth, the particles streaming from the sun
虽然在地球上看，太阳放射出的粒子和太阳风是一种辐射来源
and the solar wind are a source of radiation,
further out these same particles maintain protective bubble.
但这些粒子实际上形成了一个保护罩
The heliosphere.
即 太阳圈
It helps deflect and slow cosmic rays
它能削减衰弱从星际空间来的宇宙射线
from interstellar space
protecting the solar system from ionizing radiation.
减少电离辐射对太阳系的破坏
But the sun has an 11 year activity cycle.
不过太阳的活跃周期是11年
So this protection fluctuates.
所以这种保护效力是不稳定的
The flux of cosmic rays on earth is much lower
当太阳活跃的时候，到达地球的宇宙射线流量明显更少
when the sun is active than when it's dormant.
In the history of our planet,
地球生命演化的过程中
cosmic rays may have played an even larger role
宇宙射线或许起到了不可忽略的作用
flipping bits, not in electronics,
它翻转的不再是电子设备中的比特
but in the genetic codes of living organisms,
而是生物的遗传密码
providing some of the variation
从此诞生了通过自然选择无法产生的突变
on which natural selection acts.
Maria Vindevogel is now a member
玛丽亚·温德沃格尔现在是比利时众议院的议员了
of the Belgium Chamber of Representatives,
elected by people, not a particle,
这次是由人民选出来的，而非粒子
but her story is a reminder of the zillions of particles
但是她的故事提醒着我们
winding their way through the universe
在宇宙中有这些数不胜数的
for millions or billions of years.
漂泊了亿万年的粒子
One of which might at any moment,
不知在某个时刻  就会有个粒子
change your life by passing through a tiny transistor
撞上了一个小小的二极管，我们的一生也因此
and cra....
而改…